I hear from lots of people every day who
are concerned about how their diet is
affecting their health they need answers
based on facts in other words from the
peer-reviewed medical literature and
that is what I'm here for Welcome to the
nutrition facts podcast I'm your host Dr
Michael Gregor today we answer a wide
variety of your questions like whether
or not we should include protein
supplements the potential benefits of
niin the diet and the effects of a vegan
diet on irritable bowel syndrome let's
get your
questions okay first question 23y old
want to build a lot of muscle for sport
is it healthy to eat 1.5 grams protein
per kilogram body weight if it's 100%
from Whole Food plant-based sources and
no point of the daily dozen is
missed so in H age and the anti-aging
literature in general it really focuses
on protein restriction reducing ones int
take down to recommended levels which
should be about half that 08 uh grams
for healthy gram body weight and that's
for a whole variety of reasons which I
talk about and at high levels of protein
doesn't matter in terms of for example
igf-1 activation this um pro-aging
cancer promoting hormone uh at high
enough levels of protein intake doesn't
matter whether you're doing animal or um
plant protein you still get a boost and
igf when it's only when you're down down
to recommended levels where you get a
boost in um from animal protein sources
but not from plant protein sources so I
uh recommend you cutting down now I know
you say wait a second do I have to uh is
it like you know the Seesaw do I have
like you know at the expense of muscles
do I need to to live longer I think
people really really overestimate the
benefit that they're going to get from
muscles in terms of protein
supplementation so for for example to
older men and women there's no benefit
to adding extra protein for muscle mass
muscle strength or performance it's just
not true I mean look at the latest meta
analysis and no statistically
significant change period across the
board now uh that's not true in younger
men and women middle-aged and young as
this questioner is um but so last I
checked there are 26 randomized control
trials in middleaged and younger
individuals for adding protein to boost
Lane mass and 25 out of 26 failed
95% failed to show any significant
increase in Lan body mass okay but
enough of them trended in that direction
even though they didn't hit statistical
significance that when you put them all
together in a meta analysis um you get
on average like a 03 kilogram so less
than a pound increase over 13 weeks of
an extra 40 grams of protein a day added
to a resistance training program um so I
think that's a lot less than people
think um and of course they're looking
at lean mass right lean mass can be
water retention can be liver
inflammation or or or kidney INF
smelling you know um there's actually
not a great correlation between changes
in lean mass and the gold standard um uh
measurement of muscle mass which is
muscle mass measure an MRI and for stats
Geeks out there that's an R value of 049
which really weak correlation so even
getting more lean mass doesn't mean what
we really care about which is
appendicular lean mass you know like uh
you know thigh circumference or arm
circumference Etc so I would encourage
you to um not overdo it next up what
about plant stanols yeah so there
phytosterols and stanols so there are
these cholesterol like components in
nuts and seeds prenominal um that
actually kind of fool our body and think
it's cholesterol and so are absorb I
mean our cholesterol Transporters in our
small intestine but actually AR in
cholesterol don't act as cholesterol so
we're just basically dump back in the
intestine to kind of recirculate and so
actually prevent the absorption of some
cholesterol either going in our mouth or
in this case cholesterol made by our
liver dumped in the intestine to get rid
of it if not enough fiber to Glam onto
it um or if there's these these
phytosterols and stanols to kind of uh
block those receptor bath ways um then
they'll just get reabsorbed and you can
retain your high cholesterol so on the
portfolio diet um which was created um
by one of my favorite scientists at the
University of Toronto Dr David Jenkins
the guy who came up with a glycemic
index it's a plant-based diet but so
that cuts down on the big three things
that increase your cholesterol which is
trans fats saturated fats and dietary
cholesterol and that's enough for most
people so if you just do those three
things then you know the bell curves
like 68 LDL 68 which is right where we
want to be for primary prevention uh but
look it's a bell curve so some people do
even better than that and some people
because genetic predisposition are
higher even cutting out those things and
so if you have a gen predisposition it's
not something to throw your hands up in
the air you all you just have to work
harder at it okay what are you going to
do to work hard if you cut out all the
bad stuff then it's a matter of adding
healthy foods wi's diet that pull
cholesterol from your system um and
different foods drop your cholesterol
using different mechanisms so Jenkins
had this brilliant idea let's have a
portfolio of different foods that pull
cholesterol down from different ways and
so like adding you know beans and soy
and viscous soluble fiber rich foods
like slimy foods like okra oatmeal
eggplant things like that pull your
cholesterol down um and one of the
things in the original borolo diet I
know that's gone through a couple
different kind of transitions was a uh
supplement was a uh I think the original
one was actually a margarine containing
um phytosterols but you can take in a
supplement form um and that is one
mechanism to bring cherol down he was
able to show you can bring cholesterol
down within two weeks faster than the
Statin and as good as a first generation
stud all just with you know dietary
intervention now whether I'm not sure
what what role that plays in the current
portfolio diet I actually just pulled uh
last week all the portfolio diet studies
um it's about a hundred of them and you
know I realized that you know I haven't
really done a video about portfolio di
this super you know well-published well
researched thing I've kind of mentioned
it peripherally and so I'm going to do
whole video series and we'll see what
the current kind of thinking of it is
but um at the time that was definitely
one of the strategies and of course
there's all sorts of other things you
know I talk about black cumin and amla
and other things that drop cholesterol
and so we could beef up the pill diet
although beef up is probably not the
right word okay what's
next um just discovered they have a Rena
lesion how to best prepare for surgery
oh that's a good question you know one
of the things important for surgery is
ironically just after I talked about how
we need to restrict protein is getting
more than just the recommended minimum
protein so for example people with
pressure ulcers heal better at higher
protein intakes um it's probably
actually still below the average
American protein intake so uh we tend to
get about 70% more protein than we need
but so I forget the pressure ulid data
is like 1.1 1.2 grams it's a lot of
protein but that optimized healing rates
and so
presumably so on a Day-Day basis it's
all about kind of maintaining growth not
accelerating growth um but during times
of immune activation trying to fight off
infection or in terms of wound healing
right there is a lot of growth that has
to happen um in terms of healing that
wound same thing with like healing from
my tatto to or sunburn or there's all
sorts of times where extra protein might
come in handy so that's something so if
you really are right at the recommended
protein intake I would recommend
boosting it for um the healing process
with any kind of major
surgery next
up okay Whole Food plant-based so
basically blood long-term blood blood
sugar control and uh um body mass index
all good but has some higher LDL
cholesterol certainly than I'd like oh
and the question is should I eliminate
nuts and seeds to avoid saturate fat
well nuts and seeds actually lower your
cholesterol not raise it um and one nut
walnuts have been trying to actually
improve artery function um so I would I
would do the I would go the portfolio
diet route you can Google that and find
out all the foods to add to your diet to
reduce it down or you can also go on
nutrition vac or put in LDL and pull up
all the other things um Can can drop
your cholesterol
lower okay next up oh hyos nasin oh I
talk a lot about nasin oh so nasin is
one of the um NAD uh precursors yeah so
it's interesting so there there's some
really excellent early data on nasin
reducing cardiovascular risk uh the
problem is it has this flushing reaction
so like a hot
flash um and so what the far
pharmaceutical industry did is made an
extended release version which doesn't
have that flushing reaction fantastic
but it turns out it doesn't appear to
have the cardiovascular disease benefits
so all the early studies so ni and
benefits later studies show no benefits
or even worse actually increasing
mortality when added to a Statin that's
not good so uh and the ref fleshing
reaction is um is is probably benign
like but it's uncomfortable so currently
uh you know NYS been removed from all
the major guidelines um because um all
these big trials show that didn't work
although is it because NYS really
doesn't work or just the extended
release NYS doesn't work U may increase
the risk of diabetes like stattin does
stattin do again maybe that's just the
long release the extended release
version so but I until we know Morey
would not be my first choice although
there may be um a few medical niches in
which it may still be used it's not
certainly uh a Frontline therapy anymore
okay longtime follower fan I'm all in on
the daily dozen for those who don't
realize that's all the kind of things I
encourage people to Fender their daily
routine it's kind of an
aspirational uh you know message to
encourage people to eat the healthy
healthy foods into their daily life but
RV cooking show is saying let too much
food no no that's fine no that's the
whole I mean that's um again we're just
trying to crowd out some of the less
healthy options uh it's just
aspirational do the best you can and
look and if you're a you know some
endurance athlete who eats 5,000
calories a day that's a minimum you know
you can eat all the healthy plant Foods
you want uh don't worry about it
okay next up Michelle says my post on
eggs on Instagram caused quite a stir
and he and any additional information
and I clarify things the many denters
yeah you know it's a checkup program
with eggs you know and so you know every
cart and sold a little bit money gets
controlled by this government agency to
promote eggs uh they do all the you same
thing with dairy that's where like the
milk mustache ads and everything comes
from National carman's Beef Association
does well um and so there's just a lots
of there's just millions of dollars
available to kind of try to convince
people ex ex are good for you but
unfortunately you know the largest and
longest uh study on uh on Dy and healthy
nihp study found that even half an AG a
day associated with increased ooc cause
mortality after controlling further
factors meaning living a significantly
shorter life the Harvard studies found
that any replacing any um animal protein
including egg protein poultry fish with
plant protein uh associated with with um
significantly longer life L all cause
mortality whether it's the protein
itself or whether it's just because the
most concentrated form of dieric
cholesterol that's probably the number
one reason and even most of the studies
80% of studies funded by the egg
industry show that eating eggs increases
uh your cholesterol so it's amazing that
they're able to kind of
spin uh spin the science to that they
have but um I would encourage people to
minimize their consumption look doesn't
matter what you your birthday holiday
special occasions on a day-to-day basis
really should try to eat healthy which
means cutting down on processed foods
meat eggs dairy salt sugar maximize
their intake of fruits vegetables whole
grains legums beans slippies chickes
lentils nuts and seeds herbs and spices
mushrooms basically real food that grows
out of the ground these are our
healthiest choices next up Ocean Parkway
for 1949 asks the absorption of
nutrients from hes tea impacted by soy
milk and or
banana well maybe banana right because
the polyphenol oxidase enzyme so we
would be concerned that those um
polyphenols in habiscus tea which is why
we drink it um would be affected however
the soy milk we don't have data on hitin
soy milk but we do have on the
chlorogenic acids the The Beneficial
antioxid and coffee and soy milk
although they're Bound in the small
intestine they're released in the lower
intestine
um and so they doesn't impair the
antioxidant boost that we get from
drinking
coffee um like dairy milk um so I would
assume soy milk be fine but that sounds
disgusting iisc you know habiscus is is
like sour and yet I don't know but look
do whatever you want but yeah shouldn't
shouldn't be a problem but bananas
probably would so I would eat your
banana separate from your viscous tea if
you wanted to get all the nutrition of
the abys tea um rather than just some of
the
nutrition all right next up Caroline
it's safe to eat store-bought frozen
fruit straight from the freezer straight
from the freezer without defrosting oh
concerns about potential pathogens oh
eat it frozen yeah no absolutely is it
safe to eat starb bar food yeah no AB if
you look at my freezer it's half Frozen
greens half frozen berries and although
sometimes I warm it up put like oatmeal
or something yeah you can make smoothies
F
fantastic um yeah they are washed before
they're Frozen um and so we shouldn't
have to worry about it uh worry about
you know like uh getting some like
Hepatitis A from eating um frozen fruit
great good question okay jbo says normal
cholesterol great
well normal normal for the human species
or normal for a society where nor one
causes death as heart disease but we
assume you have a good l Del um but HL
is too low that doesn't matter HL is not
a causal risk factor for ares we used to
think it was so-called good cholesterol
actually helped um although Associated
um with lower risk cardiovascular
disease It's associated in a way that
having ashtray is associated with
getting lung cancer it's not the ashtray
it's the you know it's the uh the fact
that you're smoking um that's so I have
a whole video about it just typing HDL
into nutrition facts that to pop up it's
in some coconut oil uh or coconut milk
video I think um yeah so don't need to
worry about it um so yeah it's not a
cause of risk factor we don't worry
about it we care about on LDL
cholester okay how much oh how much this
is fancy question Martin says how much
ground mustard meaning ground mustard
seed like powdered mustard should we add
to frozen vegetables to add back the
Lost enzymes from the freezing process
so cool okay um so it's not the freezing
process kills the enzyme but it's the
heating um you know vegetables are
blanched before they're frozen to to so
that they don't rot in the freezer um to
inactivate the enzymes but then how you
g to make your sulphoraphane from your
glucose inates for people who are like
what the hell are you talking about um
check out my video on nutritionfacts.org
where I talk about how um you either
your crucius vegetables raw or you hack
and hold you chop them up Let the enzyme
do its job because the uh precursors and
the end product that you're looking at
sorane what you're interested in are
both heat stable but the enzymes not
that makes it that makes that conversion
so you chop it up let the enzyme do its
jop then you can cook all you want uh
the problem is the the the frozen
vegetables come kind of precooked in a
way so you add some enzyme how do you
add enzyme you add powdered cruciferous
vegetable mustard greens are a vegetable
mustard greens come from mustard seeds
powdered mustard seeds is a spice so
these researchers like can we just
sprinkle a little mustard powder onto
our precooked greens and get all that
sof florane yes how cool is that um uh
one milligram is almost imperceptible
but uh just a Sprinkle little sprinkle
that you can hardly even taste you can
watch the video but I think it was like
132 of a teaspoon or something was just
like a teeny little teeny little
sprinkle it's all you need anyway okay
next up are there any reliable data
sources on how a vegan D can help combat
um uh the kind of diarrheal component of
uh IBS most diets are so limited have
very little
effect um so we're talking about
irritable
bow um and uh I do so I would just type
irritable bowel into nutrition.org um
it's mostly surrounding about improving
your gut Flora by using lots of
prebiotics um to to Tamp down an
inflammation because many of the
postbiotics made by our good fiber
feeders um have anti-inflammatory action
like butat um so just yeah uh check it
out on nutritionfacts.org
okay next up hydris ah uh which is kind
of too much uh fluid in the brain oh
debilitating headaches pressure that's
not good so would eating healthy make a
difference in pain and symptoms I've
never run across anything that would
suggest so um if it gets uh significally
bad you there's you can surgically have
a a shunt implanted for like normal
pressure hydrophilus but I have not run
across anything uh died lifestyle
although I don't think I've ever looked
specifically so don't take that to me
there isn't anything we can do I've just
hadn't run across it we would love it if
you could share with us your stories
about Reinventing Your Health through
evidence-based nutrition go to
nutritionfacts.org testimonials we may
be able to share it on social media to
help Inspire others if you see any
graphs charts Graphics images or studies
mentioned here please go to the
nutrition facts podcast landing page
there you'll find all the detailed
information you need plus links to all
the sources we site for each of these
topics my latest book how not to AG is
out now premiering at number two on the
New York Times best sers list check it
out at your local public library of
course all the proceeds of the sales of
all my books goes directly to charity
nutritionfacts.org is a nonprofit
science-based Public Service where you
can sign up for free daily updates on
the latest nutrition research with
bite-size videos and articles everything
on the website is free there are no ads
no corporate sponsorships no Kickbacks
strictly
non-commercial I'm not selling anything
I just put up as a public service as a
labor of love as a tribute to my
grandmother whose own life was saved
with evidence-based nutrition